Collection of Ephemera Relating to the Marketing of Books, 1742-2014: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Publishing Ephemera Dated In the 1900s, 1900-1999; 11 boxes (10 partial)
  - [Order form for remaining titles from the Press after a hiatus from publishing], 1942; 37384; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, tall 4to (316 mm.); order form filled out by Emerson G. Wulling, requesting 2 copies of The Constitution of the United States of America; handwritten note in right-hand margin from the House's printer, Edmund Thompson, informing Wulling that the title he has requested is sold out. Previous folds.
  - James Hendrickson announces that he is now available on a free lance basis to publishers, business organizations and individuals..., 1945; 37295; portion of 1 box
    New York: James Hendrickson
    Bifolium, 4to; announcement of Hendrickson's availability as a designer and supervisor of the printing of books; reduced facsimiles of book jackets, menus, and pages designed by Hendrickson.
  - Torre, Vincent: Vincent Torre at the Ink-Well Press, 1955; 36427; portion of 1 box
    New York: Ink-Well Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; Vincent Torre illustrations throughout; prospectus of the works designed and illustrated by Vincent Torre and published by the press.
  - Konglomerati magazine, 1970; 37517; portion of 1 box
    Single folded sheet, 32mo; prospectus for this periodical edited, designed, and printed by Richard Mathews and Barbara Russ. Integral order form.
  - Konglomerati magazine, 1970; 37523; portion of 1 box
    Single sheet folded into 8-sided pamphlet; illustrated prospectus for the forthcoming Volume six of the Magazine.
  - [Order form brochure], 1978; 37522; portion of 1 box
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet; integral order form; prospectus for Concrete II and the Konglomerati Magazine tipped in.
  - Bonnardot, Alfred: The mirror of the Parisian bibliophile...translated by Theodore W. Koch. Illustrated by José Longoria, 1931; 37537; portion of 1 box
    Author: Bonnardot, Alfred
    Bifolium, folio; illustrated prospectus with extracts from reviews and letters received. Inscribed by the translator.
  - Fine books which are "Collector's items" for only $5 each!, 1937; 37396; portion of 1 box
    8vo, unpaginated; catalogue of titles from the Heritage Press and the Limited Editions Club, including Charles Dickens's "The Personal History of David Copperfield," Abbé Prevost's "The Story of Manon Lescaut," Shakespeare's "The Tragedy of Romeo and Juliet," and Nathaniel Hawthorne's "The Scarlet Letter," illustrated by W.A. Dwiggins.
  - Audubon, John James: Audubon's America. The narratives and experiences of...Edited by Donald Culross Peattie, 1940; 37534; portion of 1 box
    Author: Audubon, John James
    New York: Houghton Mifflin
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 4to; color portrait and specimen print (Putorius Vison [Mink]); two editions available, the Limited Edition consisting of 515 signed and numbered copies, and the Regular Edition.
  - White, Newman Ivey: Shelley, 1940; 37503; portion of 1 box
    Author: White, Newman Ivey
    8vo, unpaginated; original salmon printed wrappers (slightly soiled); facsimile and illustrations (one in color); prospectus for White's biography of Percy Bysshe Shelley; specimen page (445) provided; order form laid in.
  - Benét, William Rose: Mother Goose. A comprehensive collection of rhymes...Illustrated by Roger Duvoisin, 1943; 37395; portion of 1 box
    Author: Benét, William Rose
    Bifolium, 12mo; illustrated prospectus; integral order form addressed to the distributor, Argus Book Shop, Chicago.
  - Stein, Gertrude: Picasso...Music: Virgil Thomson, 1992; 37692; portion of 1 box
    New York: JHW Editions
    8vo, unpaginated; prospectus of Stein's two prose essays on Picasso ("Picasso," 1909, and "If I Told Him: A Completed Portrait of Picasso," 1923), with Virgil Thomson's musical portrait "Bugles and Birds: A Portrait of Picasso," 1940; cloth-covered clam box hand-made for the edition by Judi Conant; printing, typesetting, and binding by The Stinehour Press. Order form laid in.
    Filed under.
  - Hergesheimer, Joseph.: The works, 1919; 45016; portion of 1 box
    Author: Hergesheimer, Joseph.
    New York: Knopf, Alfred A.
    Broadside (7 3/4 x 4 3/4 inches); printed on blue paper; previous folds, else fine. Advertisement for 5 works by Hergesheimer, including "The Lay of Anthony," "Mountain Blood," "Gold and Iron," "The Three Black Pennys," and "Java Head".
  - Melville, Herman: Moby Dick, 1930; 42493; portion of 1 box
    Chicago: Lakeside Press.
    Collection of prospectuses from the Press relating to the 1930 publication of Melville's "Moby Dick"; mostly very good or better. Items include "Give Us Small Books"; "The Christening of 'Moby Dick'"; and the large 4to brochure "Four American Books".
  - A book-list from Hawthorn House, 1936; 37382; portion of 1 box
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 16mo; list includes "Cherry Ripe" by A.E. Coppard with decorations by Valenti Angelo; and "Maps in Miniature: Notes Critical and Historical on their use on postage stamps" by Walter Klinefelter. With envelope in which this prospectus was mailed, addressed to Emerson G. Wulling and postmarked Dec. 7, 1936.
  - Gifford, Humfrey: A posie of gilloflowers each differing from other in colour and odour, yet all sweet...edited with an introduction by F.J. Harvey Darton, 1933; 37300; portion of 1 box
    Author: Gifford, Humfrey
    London: Hawthornden Press
    Bifolium, 4to; prospectus of a reprint of a work originally published in 1580; specimen page (76) provided; integral order form addressed to Maggs Brothers, London. Text in red and black, previous folds.
  - The first series, 1970; 39395; portion of 1 box
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 4to; illustrations; previous fold, else fine. Order form and envelope laid in. With original envelope in which this catalogue was mailed. TLS from William J. Whitaker.
  - First list 1930, 37402; 1 of 2 copies
    12mo, pp. 6; original blue printed wrappers; titles include Christopher Marlowe's "Tamburlaine" and Dante Alighieri's "La Vita Nuvoa," with D.G. Rossetti's translation.
  - First list 1930, 37406; 1 of 2 copies
    12mo, pp. 6; original blue printed wrappers; titles include Christopher Marlowe's "Tamburlaine" and Dante Alighieri's "La Vita Nuvoa," with D.G. Rossetti's translation. Order form laid in.
  - Galt, Margot Fortunato: The country's way with rain, 1993; 37711; portion of 1 box
    Author: Galt, Margot Fortunato
    St. Paul, Minnesota: Kutenai Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus for a collection of poems; designed by Emily Strayer and limited to 150 copies. One of the copies has an invitation to a book signing and reading by the author.
  - Fuller, Margaret: The complete history of the deluge in verse and pictures, 1936; 37385; 2 copies
    Bifoliun, 8vo; illustrated prospectus for this children's book to be illustrated with 22 drawings in color; illustrated specimen page (9).
  - Viguers, Ruth Hill, Marcia Dalphin, and Bertha Mahony Miller: Illustrators of children's books 1946-1956, 1958; 37282; 2 copies
    Author: Viguers, Ruth Hill, Marcia Dalphin, and Bertha Mahony Miller
    Boston: Horn Book
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 12mo; illustrated prospectus provides table of contents, reduced specimen pages, and publication information. "Reviewers' comment" printed on the back.
  - Wood engravings. Being an impression from the original blocks in the collection at the Glad Hand Press, 1975; 37468; 2 copies
    Stamford, Connecticut: Robert M. Jones
    Bifolium, 4to; illustrated prospectus for this pictorial work displaying woodblocks from the 17th century through 1940; edition limited to 100 copies. Distributed by the Chiswick Book Shop, Sandy Hood, CT.
  - A 1981 checklist of titles, 37515; 2 copies
    12mo, unpaginated; list includes poetry, children's books, every volume of the Konglomerati magazine, and forthcoming titles; also lists Ruth Pettis's "The Goudy Presence at Konglomerati Press". Integral order form.
  - Some recent and forthcoming publications, 1928; 37284; 2 copies
    Shaftesbury: High House Press
    Single folded sheet, 12mo; list of recent and forthcoming titles, including "Rymes of the Minstrels: selections from a fifteenth-century manuscript" and William Shenstone's "A Pastoral Ballad".
  - Fine books for children, 1938; 37426; 2 copies
    16mo, unpaginated; original pictorial wrappers; illustrated catalogue of titles from the press, including Kenneth Grahame's "The Reluctant Dragon"; and William Allen Butler's "Tom Twist".
  - Hunter, Dard: My life with paper, 1947; 37508; 2 copies
    Author: Hunter, Dard
    Broadside, folio (280 mm.); prospectus for this book historian's autobiography; with praise and commentaries by other bibliophiles. Integral order form. Printed on yellow-green paper with blue ink, previous folds.
  - Landwehr, John: VOC. A bibliography of publications relating to the Dutch East India Company 1902-1800. Edited by Peter van der Krogt. Introduction by C.R. Boxer. Preface by G. Schilder, 1991; 37302; 2 copies
    Author: Landwehr, John
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 4to; includes facsimiles, specimen pages (248, 293), illustrations, and integral order form for this bibliography, limited to 1000 copies. Previous fold.
  - Roberts, Verne L. and Ivy Trent: Bibliotheca mechanica, 1991; 37279; 2 copies
    Author: Roberts, Verne L. and Ivy Trent
    New York: Jonathan A. Hill
    Bifolium, 4to; illustrated prospectus for a reference work drawing from the Verne L. Roberts collection of rare and imporant works "in the fields of mechanics, biomechanics, the strength of materials, and the history of technology". Limited to 150 deluxe and 1000 regular copies and printed by W. Thomas Taylor. Specimen page (158) provided.
  - Leonardo da Vinci.: The codex Atlanticus, Vol. I, 1973; 44701; 2 copies
    Square folio, unpaged; staplebound self-wrappers, upper cover folding plate printed on verso; color and plain illustrations throughout; minor discoloration and foxing, else about fine. Typescript letter on Corporation letterhead and blank order form laid in. Prospectus for the first of a twelve-volume limited facsimile reprint of the Codex.
  - Paultre, Roger: Les images du livre. Emblêmes et devises, 1991; 37281; 2 copies
    Author: Paultre, Roger
    Paris: Hermann
    Bifolium, 4to; illustrated prospectus, includes five reduced reproductions of works cited in the book proper.
  - [Rogers, Bruce]: A keepsake for collectors of Rogersiana [heading title], 1935; 42470; 2 copies
    Author: [Rogers, Bruce]
    Philadelphia: Lanston Monotype Machine Company.
    Broadside (174 mm.); fine. Keepsake on Rogers's Oxford Lectern Bible.
  - A checklist of the books the Janus Press published in 1977, 37479; 2 copies, 1 not in envelope
    Two leaves, 4to; list of titles, some already out of print, from the press, including Ted Hughes's poem "Chiasmadon" and "Bread and Puppet White Horse Butcher," written and illustrated by Peter Schummann. Text in tan and black, blue decorative boarders, previous fold. In an envelope.
  - [Christmas catalogue], 1979; 37520; 2 copies?
    Bifolium, 8vo; list of titles and notecards available from the press; integral order form.
  - [Christmas catalogue], 1983; 37524; 2 copies?
    Bifolium, 8vo; catalogue of titles and notecards available from the Press. Integral order form.
  - Zinman, Michael: The American Bible. Original leaves from rare and historic bibles printed in the colonies and the United States during the seventeenth, eighteenth, and nineteenth centuries...with an introduction by Mark Noll, 1993; 37297; 7 copies
    Author: Zinman, Michael
    Ardsley, New York: Haydn Foundation for the Cultural Arts
    4to, unpaginated; original gilt-stamped red wrappers; facsimiles and illustrations of the work throughout. Edition limited to 100 sets. One copy has a letter signed by Barbara Weingarten.
  - Shakespeare, William: Shakespeare: A review and a preview, 1939; 37966; portion of 1 box
    Folio, mixed paginations; 4 plates; original linen, printed in red and housed in brown box, fine. An illustrated prospectus for the Club's editions of the works of Shakespeare; includes the section: "What has been said of Shakespeare," by John Milton and others; George Macy's "A note upon a new Shakespeare"; and "Pages and pictures from the new Shakespeare". Illustrated pamphlet "Some notes upon a project for an illustrated Shakespeare" and order form laid in.
  - Messrs. Longmans, Green, and Co. have the pleasure of announcing that they have arranged with the Trustees of the late William Morris for the publication of a limited edition of the following eight volumes, 1901; 39226; portion of 1 box
    London: Longmans, Green, and Co.
    Bifolium, 4to; text printed only on front side; edges very mildly toned, else fine. Titles include The Odyssey of Homer and The Aeneids of Virgil. This series to honor Morris's original plan to publish the full series of his works at the Kelmscott Press, a project cut short by his death in 1896. This edition to be limited to 315 copies.
  - A list of books in belles lettres issued in choice and limited editions. MDCCCXCI-MDCCCCVII, 1907; 38145; portion of 1 box
    Portland, Maine: Mosher Books
    8vo, pp. 67, [1]; original blue wrappers printed in red and black (some minor soiling), toning along edges, small loss to lower-right hand corners not affecting text. A complete list of titles from all the series of the press, including "The Poems of Edgar Allan Poe with an essay on his poetry by Andrew Lang" and Robert Browning's "Pippa Passes," both from the Old World Series; "Prose Selections by Oscar Wilde" from the Brocade Series; a complete list of the contents from the serial "The Bibelot"; W.B. Yeats's "The Land of Heart's Desire" and "A Little Garland of Celtic Verse," both from the Lyric Garland series; "A Little Book of Nature Thoughts from Walt Whitman" from the Vest Pocket series; Dante Gabriel Rossetti's "Hand and Soul"; "The Poems of Oscar Wilde"; Robert Louis Stevenson's "Father Damien"; Rennell Rodd's "Rose Leaf and Apple Leaf" with an introduction by Oscar Wilde; and Percy Bysshe Shelley's "A Defense of Poetry". Index at end. Order form, "Special Instructions," and envelope laid in.
  - The plan of Minneapolis: a brief description of the plans prepared by the civic commission of Minneapolis and now exhibited at the Minneapolis Institute of Arts, 1915; 41775; portion of 1 box
    Minneapolis: Minneapolis Institute of Arts.
    8vo, pp. 12; original brown wrappers printed in dark brown; light edge wear, else near fine. "The plans in this room are based upon the certainty that the city limits of Minneapolis will contain, within thirty years, a population of more than one million."
  - Specimens in miniature of what it has given in the past and will bring in the future, 1919; 37816; portion of 1 box
    Washington, D.C.: National Geographic Magazine
    12mo, unpaginated; illustrated prospectus and retrospectus of the magazine's work, mostly shown through the use of color photographic illustrations, including pictures of Great Danes, a dance of North Africa, "the barn owl: a relentless enemy of rodents," "the Virginia deer: a food staple of the earliest American colonists," "the land of the Nile," elephants of Ceylon, a woman of Bethlehem, etc.
  - De Ricci, Seymour: The book collector's guide...A practical handbook of British and American bibliography, 1921; 38038; portion of 1 box
    New York: Maggs Bros.
    Bifolium, 16mo; prospectus advertises that "This will enable, at a glance, any owner of a first edition of, say, Byron, Dickens or Thackeray, to ascertain exactly what standard copies are sold for".
  - Heywood, Thomas: The first and second parts of King Edward the fourth. A facsimile reprint of the unique copy of the first edition (1599) in the library of Charles W. Clark. With an introductory note by Seymour de Ricci, 1922; 38043; portion of 1 box
    Author: Heywood, Thomas
    London: Maggs Bros.
    Broadside, 16mo (153 mm.); edition limited to 150 copies. "No Shakespearean library should be without it."
  - Theocritus: The idyls...rendered into English prose by Andrew Lang. Illustrated after drawings by W. Russell Flint, 1922; 39283; portion of 1 box
    Author: Theocritus
    London: Medici Society Ltd.
    Bifolium, 4to; 2 decorative vignettes; edges a bit toned, else fine. Specimen pages provided. A list of Riccardi Press books listed on back.
  - A list of books in belles lettres issued in choice and limited editions, 1925; 38144; portion of 1 box
    8vo, pp. 44; original cream printed wrappers (light soiling), fine. Catalogue includes titles from various series, including Charles Baudelaire's "Poems in Prose in the "Ideal Series"; Percy Bysshe Shelley's "Lyrical Poems" in the "Lyric Garland" series; and a memorial facsimile edition of Walt Whitman's "Leaves of Grass". Also provides complete list of contents from the serial "The Bibelot" and index. Order forms laid in.
  - Eden, Emily: The semi-attached couple...with an introduction by John Gore, 1927; 36393; portion of 1 box
    Author: Eden, Emily
    London: Elkin Mathews & Marrot Limited
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus for works forming part of the Rescue Series, "designed to afford a number of pleasing and dignified reprints...of the best among the many novels of bygone generations which, after having deserved and achieved a wide vogue and reputation, have gone out of circulation and long been unknown to the general reader." A specimen page (82) of the Semi-Attached Couple is provided, along with other volumes in the series, including Marmion Savage's The Bachelor of the Albany and Eaton Stannard Barrett's The Heroine. Press opinions of these two latter titles are given on the back leaf. Small tear to bottom of spine, discoloration at edges.
  - Salvator, Ludwig Louis: Los Angeles in the sunny seventies...Translated by Marguerite Eyer Wilbur. Introduction by Phil Townsend Hanna, 1929; 38048; portion of 1 box
    Author: Salvator, Ludwig Louis
    Los Angeles: Bruce McCallister
    Bifolium, 8vo; propsectus provides "An Opinion by Robert Ernest Cowan"; edition limited to 900 copies, distributed by Jake Zeitlin; integral order form.
  - Sterne, Laurence: A sentimental journey...Hand-set in Naudin type with fifteen illustrations by Polia Chentoff, 1929; 39255; portion of 1 box
    Paris: Éditions Narcisse.
    Bifolium, 8vo; plate laid in, text printed in brown and green; previous fold, else fine. Prospectus for a limited edition of 400 copies published in conjunction with the Black Sun Press. Prices and and publication dates printed in typescript. Specimen page and a list of 3 titles in preparation included. Distributed in the United States by the Bookshop of Harry F. Marks, New York.
  - The monthly letter...Number three, August, 1929, 38015; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 4to; photographic illustration of the Club's edition of "Baron Munchausen".
  - The monthly letter...Number two, July, 1929, 38016; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 4to; photographic illustration of the Club's edition of Walt Whitman's "Leaves of Grass".
  - The monthly letter...Number seven, December, 1929, 38011; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 4to; specimen page from Carl Purington Rollins' "Snow-Bound," which was published in January, 1930.
  - The monthly letter...Number four, September, 1929, 38014; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 4to; title page and specimen illustration, by Alexander King, of the Club's edition of "Gulliver's Travels".
  - The monthly letter...Number five, October, 1929, 38013; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 4to; title page of Walt Whitman's "Leaves of Grass," designed by Frederic Warde, which was published by the Club the following month.
  - The monthly letter...Number six, November 1929, 38012; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 4to; yellow and black wood-cut illustration by John Held, Jr. for "The Travels of Baron Munchausen," the Club's December publication.
  - TLS dated September 23, 1929, portion of 1 box
  - TLS dated November 2, 1929, portion of 1 box
  - TLS dated October 4, 1929, portion of 1 box
  - Arms, Dorothy Noyes: Churches of France...with fifty full-page etchings reproduced by special process and one original signed etching by John Taylor Arms, 1929; 38077; portion of 1 box
    Author: Arms, Dorothy Noyes
    Bifolium, 4to; full-page black and white illustration by John Taylor Arms; edition limited to 200 copies. Previous folds.
  - First list, 1929; 38081; portion of 1 box
    London: Mandrake Press
    Small 8vo, unpaginated; original yellow wrappers, sunning to edges, distributor's rubber stamp, very good. Literary quotations printed on wrapper versos. Titles from the press include "The Paintings of D.H. Lawrence" and Giovanni Boccaccio's "The Amorous Fiametta".
  - A list of books in belles lettres issued in choice and limited editions, 1929; 38143; portion of 1 box
    Small 8vo, pp. 44; the whole printed on green paper, negligible toning, very good. Catalogue lists titles from various series, including Hilaire Belloc's "Tristan and Iseult" in the "Old World Series"; Robert Browning's "Italy My Italy" in the "Venetian Series"; Elizabeth Barrett Browning's "Sonnets from the Portuguese" from the "Vest Pocket Series"; and Dante Gabriel Rossetti's "Ballads and Sonnets" in the "Quarto Series". Also provides a complete list of the table of contents for each number of the serial "The Bibelot". With index.
  - Addison, Joseph: From the Tatler, Thursday, February 9, 1709. An essay...The trial of the wine-brewers. With an introduction and an inquiry into Mr. Addison's drinking by Edward F. O'Day, 1930; 38168; portion of 1 box
    Author: Addison, Joseph
    San Francisco: John Henry Nash
    Bifolium, folio; 2 wood cut vignettes. Prospectus for this edition of Addison's essay, limited to 385 copies. "The binding is hand-made marbled paper boards in lovely wine tones".
  - Its second series, 1930-1931, 37963; portion of 1 box
    8vo, pp. 18; original printed yellow wrappers, fine. Titles in the catalogue include William Makepeace Thakeray's "Vanity Fair, a novel without a hero"; "Tales by the brothers Grimm"; Victor Hugo's "Notre Dame de Paris"; Nathaniel Hawthorne's "The Marble Faun, or The romance of Monte Beni"; and Leo Tolstoi's "Anna Karenina". Order form laid in.
  - The monthly letter...number nine, February, 1930, 38010; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 4to; color specimen illustration from "Two Medieval Tales" by Robert Louis Stevenson, which was published the following month by the Club.
  - The monthly letter...Number twelve, May, 1930, 37991; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, folio; reduced specimen page and illustration by W.A. Dwiggins from Tartarin of Tarascon. This number also includes an article on Rip Van Winkle, printed by the Village Press for the Club.
  - The monthly letter...Number fifteen, August, 1930, 37988; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, folio; reproduction of a copper engraving by Rudolph Ruzicka for the Club's edition of La Fontaine's "Fables," to be published the following month. This number also includes an article on Robinson Crusoe.
  - The monthly letter...Number sixteen, September, 1930, 37987; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, folio; reproduction of a woodcut illustration by Frans Maseréel for "Notre Dame de Paris" laid in. Newsletter includes two articles, on La Fontaine's "Fables" and Victor Hugo's "Notre Dame".
  - The monthly letter...Number eleven, April, 1930, 37992; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, folio; specimen page from Rip Van Winkle, set in Kaatskill type; article, "Boccaccio and Us," printed in conjunction with the Club's publication of The Decameron.